[MUSIC]
[음악]
Other examples of document retrieval.
문서 검색의 다른 예들
Okay?
알겠죠?
So we're gonna go through a few.
몇몇 예를 살펴볼 겁니다
For example, let's take the singer Taylor Swift.
가수 테일러 스위프트를 보죠
So out of all my people,
모든 인물 중에
I'm going to select the one
이름이 테일러 스위프트인
whose name is Taylor Swift.
사람을 고릅니다
And so when I select her I can ask,
그렇게 고른 다음에
let's retrieve some documents that are similar to Taylor Swift's documents.
테일러 스위프트 문서와 유사한 다른 문서 검색을 요청합니다
In other words, who are the people, just for
즉 모델에서 테일러 스위프트와
the model, who are the people who are closest to Taylor Swift?
가까운 인물들이 누군가요?
So she's a female singer and you'll see other female
여자 가수니 같은 세대의
singers kind of the same generation like Carrie Underwood,
캐리 언더우드, 알리시아 키스, 조딘 스팍스,
Alicia Keys, Jordan Sparks, Leona Lewis.
리오나 루이스 등의 여자 가수를 보게 될 겁니다
And just a little disclaimer here, I had to go and
한 가지 말씀드리자면 누군지 몰라서
look those people up in Wikipedia because I really didn't know who they were.
위키피디아에 가서 찾아봐야 했답니다
[LAUGH] Here we go.
[웃음] 넘어가죠
Let's take another example.
다른 예를 들어보죠
So for example, the actress Angelina Jolie.
안젤리나 졸리가 있습니다
So if I take, out of all my people,
모든 인물 중 이름이 안젤리나 졸리인
I take the one whose name is Angelina Jolie.
사람을 고릅니다
And I'm now going to query my nearest neighbor
그리고 최근접 이웃 모델에 안젤리나 졸리와
model to ask who is closest to Angelina Jolie.
가장 가까운 인물이 누군지 묻습니다
And so who is closer to Angelina Jolie?
누가 안젤리나 졸리와 가장 가까울 것 같나요?
Before I press enter here, take a moment to think.
엔터를 누르기 전에 잠시 생각해봅시다
If you know anything about this actress Angelina Jolie,
안젤리나 졸리에 대해 조금이라도 안다면
you might guess who is the closest person to her, and
가장 가까운 사람이 누군지 알 수 있는데
if I run this, you'll see that the nearest neighbor is Brad Pitt.
바로 브래드 피트입니다
And we all know about the relationship between Angelina Jolie and Brad Pitt.
안젤리나 졸리와 브래드 피트의 관계는 모두 알죠
And then you see Julianne Moore, Billy Bob Thornton, George Clooney, these are all
줄리앤 무어, 빌리 밥 손튼, 조지 클루니 등 모두
actors and actresses that have been in movies actually with Angelina Jolie.
안젤리나 졸리와 영화를 함께 찍었던 배우들입니다
So, It's pretty cool.
멋지군요
We get some interesting retrieval here.
흥미로운 검색 결과가 나왔습니다
So let me show you one last cool, fun example.
마지막으로 멋지고 재밌는 예를 보여드리죠
So you might be familiar with a person called
아놀드 슈워제네거란 인물을
Arnold Schwarzenegger.
잘 아실 겁니다
The famous Terminator.
터미네이터로 유명하죠
So, I actually have to cheat here to
성을 제대로 쓰려면 컨닝을
make sure I get his last name right,
좀 해야겠네요
Schwarzenegger, okay.
슈워제네거 맞죠
Hopefully I got that right.
맞았길 바랍니다
And the question is, who are the nearest neighbors to Arnold Schwarzenegger?
이제 중요한 게 아놀드 슈워제네거와 가장 가까운 이웃은 누구인가요?
Now.
자
You may know that Arnold had a double career.
아놀드의 커리어가 두 개였다는 사실을 아시나요
So first, he start as an actor, well,
처음에는 배우, 아니 보디빌더로 시작했다가
bodybuilder, then an actor, then a politician, and became
배우로 전향했고, 그다음 정치가가 돼서
the governor of the state of California in the United States, so several lives.
캘리포니아 주지사까지 역임했죠
So what are the nearest neighbors for Arnold Schwarzenegger?
아놀드 슈워제네거의 최근접 이웃은 누구일가요?
And so you'll see Arnold Schwarzenegger.
먼저 아놀드 슈워제네거 본인을 보게 되겠죠
Then you'll see Jessie Ventura, who is like a,
그리고 레슬러이자 배우로 아놀드 슈워제네거와
Jessie Venture is a wrestler, an actor, so similar to Arnold Schwarzenegger.
유사한 제시 벤추라를 보게 되겠죠
And then a few politicians, including former
그다음 오리건, 로드 아일랜드, 미국 몇몇 주들의
governors of Oregon, and of Rhode Island and other states in the United States.
주지사들을 보게 됩니다
So now we see that the nearest neighbors for Arnold are politicians and
그러므로 아놀드의 최근접 이웃은 정치인, 배우,
actors and body builders, people like him.
actors and body builders, people like him. 보디딜더 등 그와 비슷한 사람들이죠
So this was a really cool example of just building a very simple document retrieval
TF-IDF와 최근접 이웃을 통해 아주 간단한
system using TFIDF and nearest neighbors.
문서 검색 시스템을 만들어봤습니다
Just like we learned in the module, but now taking it to practice and
이 모듈에서 배운 바와 같이 이를 실무에 활용,
finding some pretty cool documents from this Wikipedia data set.
위키피디아 데이터 세트로부터 멋진 문서를 찾아보세요
[MUSIC]
[음악]